<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  ~ Hibernate, Relational Persistence for Idiomatic Java
  ~
  ~ Copyright (c) 2008, Red Hat, Inc. and/or its affiliates  or third-party contributors as
  ~ indicated by the @author tags or express copyright attribution
  ~ statements applied by the authors.  All third-party contributions are
  ~ distributed under license by Red Hat, Inc.
  ~
  ~ This copyrighted material is made available to anyone wishing to use, modify,
  ~ copy, or redistribute it subject to the terms and conditions of the GNU
  ~ Lesser General Public License, as published by the Free Software Foundation.
  ~
  ~ This program is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
  ~ but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of MERCHANTABILITY
  ~ or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the GNU Lesser General Public License
  ~ for more details.
  ~
  ~ You should have received a copy of the GNU Lesser General Public License
  ~ along with this distribution; if not, write to:
  ~ Free Software Foundation, Inc.
  ~ 51 Franklin Street, Fifth Floor
  ~ Boston, MA  02110-1301  USA
  -->
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
        <!ENTITY versionNumber "3.1.0.GA">
        <!ENTITY copyrightYear "2004">
        <!ENTITY copyrightHolder "Red Hat Middleware, LLC.">
]>

<book lang="en">
    <bookinfo>
        <title>Hibernate Validator</title>
        <subtitle>Reference Guide</subtitle>
        <releaseinfo>&versionNumber;</releaseinfo>
        <productnumber>&versionNumber;</productnumber>
        <issuenum>1</issuenum>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/hibernate_logo_a.png" format="png" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject> 
        <copyright>
            <year>&copyrightYear;</year>
            <holder>&copyrightHolder;</holder>
        </copyright>
        <!-- include translators... -->
    </bookinfo>

  <toc/>

  <preface id="preface" revision="2">
    <title>Preface</title>

    <para>Annotations are a very convenient and elegant way to specify
    invariant constraints for a domain model. You can, for example, express
    that a property should never be null, that the account balance should be
    strictly positive, etc. These domain model constraints are declared in the
    bean itself by annotating its properties. A validator can then read them
    and check for constraint violations. The validation mechanism can be
    executed in different layers in your application without having to
    duplicate any of these rules (presentation layer, data access layer).
    Following the DRY principle, Hibernate Validator has been designed for
    that purpose.</para>

    <para>Hibernate Validator works at two levels. First, it is able to check
    in-memory instances of a class for constraint violations. Second, it can
    apply the constraints to the Hibernate metamodel and incorporate them into
    the generated database schema.</para>

    <para>Each constraint annotation is associated to a validator
    implementation responsible for checking the constraint on the entity
    instance. A validator can also (optionally) apply the constraint to the
    Hibernate metamodel, allowing Hibernate to generate DDL that expresses the
    constraint. With the appropriate event listener, you can execute the
    checking operation on inserts and updates done by Hibernate. Hibernate
    Validator is not limited to use with Hibernate. You can easily use it
    anywhere in your application as well as with any Java Persistence provider
    (entity listener provided).</para>

    <para>When checking instances at runtime, Hibernate Validator returns
    information about constraint violations in an array of
    <classname>InvalidValue</classname> s. Among other information, the
    <classname>InvalidValue</classname> contains an error description message
    that can embed the parameter values bundle with the annotation (eg. length
    limit), and message strings that may be externalized to a
    <classname>ResourceBundle</classname> .</para>
  </preface>

  <xi:include href="modules/defineconstraints.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />
  <xi:include href="modules/checkconstraints.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />
</book>